Guide to the Kentucky Miners Defense Records TAM.032
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kentucky Miners Defense Records
1931-1937
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kentucky Miners Defense
Mahler, Bessie Freiberg
Milwaukee Public Library
TAM.032
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The Kentucky Miners Defense was formed to help free miners and local mine union officials convicted of conspiracy to murder three sheriff's deputies in Evarts, Harlan County, Kentucky during the miners' strike of May 1931. The committee was headed by Herbert Mahler, a former official of the Industrial Workers of the World. The collection contains court transcripts, statements and other documents relating to the miners' cases, as well as news releases, United States Senate subcommittee hearing reports, and excerpts from the Daily Worker.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Herbert Mahler's wife, Bessie Freiberg Mahler, in 1963. The accession number 1963.009 is associated with this gift. One pamphlet (Governer Chandler Denies...) was added to the collection as a donation from the Milwaukee Public Library in 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Kentucky Miners Defense was an organization formed to help free seven imprisoned miners who had been convicted of murdering three coal company guards in Evarts, Harlan County, Kentucky during a hard-fought miners' strike in May 1931. Intense conflict between coal company agents and local authorities, on the one hand, and desperate locked-out miners, many of them homeless and destitute resulted in numerous incidents of violence. On May 5, 1931 a large group of armed miners attacked a convoy of deputies; a heavy exchange of fire, lasting thirty minutes, left 3 deputies and 1 miner dead. Local union officials W. B. Jones and William Hightower and more than forty miners were arrested in connection with the killing of the deputies. After several trials, Jones, Hightower and six others were convicted of conspiracy to commit murder, although the facts of the case were unclear.
Herbert Mahler (a former activist in the Industrial Workers of the World), director of the organization, spearheaded the publicity campaign to bring national attention to the miners' cases. Fund-raising publicity was often aimed at unions and their members since the Kentucky miners had been attempting to organize under the auspices of the United Mine Workers when they were violently blocked by the coal companies and their allies.
Sources:
American Civil Liberties Union. The Kentucky Miners Struggle. (New York: ACLU, 1932).
Hevener, John. Which Side Are You on? The Harlan County Coal Miners, 1931-39. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1978.
Publications relating to Kentucky Miners Defense. (Tamiment Library Vertical File).
Scope and Content Note
Series I, General Files, 1931-1937, consists of statements, briefs and other documents related to the cases of Bill Hudson, Chester Poore, Elzie Phillips, Jim Reynolds, W. B. Jones and William Hightower, in both Circuit and Appeals courts. Also included are reports from a United States Senate subcommittee hearing on labor conditions in Harlan and Bell Counties, Kentucky Miners Defense news releases, and excerpts from the Daily Worker documenting events related to labor unrest in Kentucky.
Series II, Transcripts, 1931-1933, contains court transcripts from the cases of Al Benson, Chester Poore, Elzie Phillips, Jim Reynolds and W. B. Jones from Harlan and Montgomery County Circuit Courts.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, General Files, 1931-1937
II, Transcripts, 1931-1933
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kentucky Miners Defense Photographs (PHOTOS 016)
John Nicholas Beffel Papers (TAM 055)
Transcripts.; Evarts (Ky.); Harlan County (Ky.); Correspondence.; Press releases.; Coal mines and mining |z Kentucky |z Harlan County.; Coal miners |z Kentucky |z Harlan County.; Kentucky Miners Defense; United Mine Workers of America; Poore, Chester.; Reynolds, Jim.; Benson, Al; Mahler, Herbert; Phillips, Elzie.; Hightower, William; Jones, W. B.; Mahler, Bessie Freiberg; Milwaukee Public Library
- Series I: General Files, 1931-1937.
  - Bloody Harlan: The Story of Four Miners Serving Life for Daring to Organize a Union, Daring to Strike, Daring to Picket; Governer Chandler Denies Pardons to Harlan Miners.(2 pamphlets), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Elzie Phillips(Harlan Circuit Court): Opening Statement by Defense Counsel John M. Robison, Jun 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Witnesses, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conditions in Coal Fields in Harlan and Bell Counties, Kentucky: Hearings Before a Subcommittee of the Committee on Manufactures(United States Congress), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: William Turnblazer (United Mine Workers of America) to W. B. Jones, Apr 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Daily Worker: Excerpts from Articles, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E. Phillips v. Commonwealth of Kentucky, Bill Hudson v. Commonwealth of Kentucky, Chester Poore v. Commonwealth of Kentucky, Jim Reynolds v. Commonwealth of Kentucky(Court of Appeals of Kentucky): Brief for Appellee, May 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kentucky Reports: "Jones v. Commonwealth. Hightower v. Same", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Map of a Part of Evarts, Kentucky and Vicinity Showing the Scene of the Killing of Jim Daniels and Others: Map No.1, Exhibit B, undated (Flat-file-folder 9)
  - News Releases, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notes: General, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - W. B. Jones v. Commonwealth of Kentucky, William Hightower vs. Commonwealth of Kentucky(Court of Appeals of Kentucky): Brief for Appellee, Feb 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - William Hightower vs. Commonwealth of Kentucky(Court of Appeals of Kentucky): Motion to Withdraw Exhibits, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Transcripts, 1931-1933.
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 1, Jan 1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 2, Jan 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 3, Jan 1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 4, Jan 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 1 (carbon copy), Jan 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 2 (carbon copy), Jan 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 3 (carbon copy), Jan 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Al Benson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 4 (carbon copy), Jan 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Bill Hudson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 1-2, Sep 1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Bill Hudson(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 3-4, Sep 1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Chester Poore(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 1-2, Sep 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Chester Poore(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 3, Sep 1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Chester Poore(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 4-5, Sep 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. E. Phillips(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 1-2, Aug 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. E. Phillips(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 3-4, Aug 1932 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. E. Phillips(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 5-6, Aug 1932 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. E. Phillips(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 7, Aug 1932 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Jim Reynolds(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 1-2, Oct 1932 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Jim Reynolds(Harlan Circuit Court): Volumes 3-4, Oct 1932 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. Jim Reynolds(Harlan Circuit Court): Volume 5, Oct 1932 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 1-2, Nov 1931 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 3-4, Nov 1931 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 5-6, Nov 1931 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 7-8, Nov 1931 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volume 9 (2 copies), Nov 1931 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 10-11, Nov 1931 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 12-13, Nov 1931 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 14-15, Nov 1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volumes 16-17, Nov 1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth of Kentucky vs. W. B. Jones(Montgomery Circuit Court): Volume 18, Nov 1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Transcript Excerpts, 1931-1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)